Bell, Abraham, and Son; Collection mss035
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Abraham Bell and Son Collection
1809-1917
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
mss035
22 cubic ft.
The collection consists of 157 volumes of business books and three boxes of financial materials, correspondence, books, scrapbooks and diaries relating to the Bell Family and the Abraham Bell and Son Company.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
The items in this manuscript group were acquired by the University Libraries in 1969. These were purchased at an auction.
Two additional ledgers were purchased from a dealer and an additional accession of financial papers, two account books, and a receipt book were purchased from Syracuse University, all in 1971.
Richard Wiles donated business correspondence and leases for the Maryland Property in 1990.
Biographical History
Abraham Bell and Son was a New York City merchant shipping firm, that specialized in the export of Southern cotton to the British Isles. The Bell family were Quakers and often did trade with people groups in England, Ireland, and Liverpool. In the 1840's the Bell's helped transport thousands of immigrants from Ireland. Abraham Bell had seven children with his first wife, and several more with his second wife. The company was said to have been on Fulton Street in New York City.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 157 volumes of business books and three boxes of financial materials, correspondence, books, scrapbooks and diaries relating to the Bell Family and the Abraham Bell and Son Company.
Includes thirty-one letter press copybooks kept daily by Abraham Bell and Son, 1837-1854; 39 volumes of account books, journals, correspondence, and other business records, 1809-1888; a record book of Irish immigrants and other passengers to the United States from Derry and Belfast, 1832-1857. There are also correspondence, diaries, and financial records of other members of this Quaker family, James W. Bell and James C. Bell, 1832-1917; record books of Elizabeth Bell, 1858; and records of Bell Brothers, a money-lending business in Yonkers, New York, 1889-1895.
Related collections of Bell family and business materials are found at Duke University, Harvard University, Louisiana State Unviersity, New-York Historical Society, Northeatern Unviersity, Tulane University, University of Michigan, University of South Carolina and the Winterthur.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized alphabetically, first by ledgers and then by foldered/boxed materials. There are no series.
Women; Travel; Ethnic Groups; Business and Industry; Agriculture; Banks and banking--Ireland; Ireland--Emigration and immigration; England--Emigration and immigration; New York (N.Y.)--Commerce; Correspondence; Account books; Bell, James W.--(James Winfred), 1929-; Abraham Bell and Son; Bell Brothers (Yonkers, N.Y.)
- Account Sales, 1823-1844 (Volume 1)
- Accounts Current, 1836-1848 (Volume 2)
- Accounts Current, 1848-1852 (Volume 3)
- Accounts Current, 1853-1857 (Volume 4)
- Accounts Current, 1877-1880 (Volume 5)
- Arrearages, 1892-1893 (Volume 6)
- Arrearages, 1892-1894 (Volume 7)
- Arrearages, 1894-1896 (Volume 8)
- Bills Receivable, 1846-1851 (Volume 9)
- Blotter, 1847-1850 (Volume 10)
- Bonds and Mortgages, 1890-1896 (Volume 11)
- Cash Book, 1832-1838 (Volume 12)
- Cash Book, 1838-1842 (Volume 13)
- Cash Book, 1844-1850 (Volume 14)
- Cash Book, 1853-1856 (Volume 15)
- Checkbook, 1833-1835 (Volume 16)
- Checkbook, 1837-1839 (Volume 17)
- Checkbook, 1844-1846 (Volume 18)
- Checkbook, 1844-1853 (Volume 19)
- Checkbook, 1846-1848 (Volume 20)
- Checkbook, 1848-1849 (Volume 21)
- Checkbook, 1849-1850 (Volume 22)
- Checkbook, 1850-1851 (Volume 23)
- Checkbook, 1851-1852 (Volume 24)
- Checkbook, 1852-1853 (Volume 25)
- Checkbook, 1853-1854 (Volume 26)
- Checkbook, 1854-1855 (Volume 27)
- Checkbook, 1858-1861 (Volume 28)
- Checkbook, 1864-1865 (Volume 29)
- Checkbook, 1865-1867 (Volume 30)
- Checkbook, 1899-1900 (Volume 31)
- Checkbook, 1900-1901 (Volume 32)
- Checkbook, 1902-1903 (Volume 33)
- Checkbook, Undated (Volume 34)
- Collections, 1844-1846 (Volume 35)
- Collections, 1864-1879 (Volume 36)
- Drafts, 1849 (Volume 37)
- Drafts, 1850-1851 (Volume 38)
- Drafts, 1851-1852 (Volume 39)
- Drafts, 1852-1853 (Volume 40)
- Drafts, 1853-1855 (Volume 41)
- Drafts, 1853-1856 (Volume 42)
- Freight Lists, 1827-1860 (Volume 43)
- Index, Undated (Volume 44)
- Index, Undated (Volume 45)
- Index, Undated (Volume 46)
- Index, Undated (Volume 47)
- Index, Undated (Volume 48)
- Index, Undated (Volume 49)
- Index, Undated (Volume 50)
- Index, Undated (Volume 51)
- Index, Undated (Volume 52)
- Index, Undated (Volume 53)
- Index, Undated (Volume 54)
- Index, Undated (Volume 55)
- Index, Undated (Volume 56)
- Index, Undated (Volume 57)
- Index, Undated (Volume 58)
- Index, Undated (Volume 59)
- Index, Undated (Volume 60)
- Index, Undated (Volume 61)
- Insurance Premiums, 1863-1864 (Volume 62)
- Interest Dates Receivable, 1877 (Volume 63)
- Invoices, 1853-1856 (Volume 64)
- Invoices Outward, 1848-1852 (Volume 65)
- Invoices Outward, 1852-1856 (Volume 66)
- Invoices Outward, 1852-1856 (Volume 67)
- Journal, 1815-1826 (Volume 68)
- Journal, 1817-1819 (Volume 69)
- Journal, 1831-1834 (Volume 70)
- Journal, 1834-1837 (Volume 71)
- Journal, 1840-1841 (Volume 72)
- Journal, 1841-1850 (Volume 73)
- Journal, 1853-1855 (Volume 74)
- Ledger, 1809-1821 (Volume 75)
- Ledger, 1824-1841 (Volume 76)
- Ledger, 1834-1835 (Volume 77)
- Ledger, 1840-1849 (Volume 78)
- Ledger, 1844-1846 (Volume 79)
- Ledger, 1850-1852 (Volume 80)
- Letter-copy Book, 1835 April 7-December 31 (Volume 81)
- Letter-copy Book, 1836 January 1-July 7 (Volume 82)
- Letter-copy Book, 1837 January 24-July 13 (Volume 83)
- Letter-copy Book, 1837 July 14-1838 February 22 (Volume 84)
- Letter-copy Book, 1838 October 2-1839 March 9 (Volume 85)
- Letter-copy Book, 1840 March 4-August 1 (Volume 86)
- Letter-copy Book, 1840 July 31-1841 February 28 (Volume 87)
- Letter-copy Book, 1841 February 26-August 12 (Volume 88)
- Letter-copy Book, 1841 August 12-1842 February 28 (Volume 89)
- Letter-copy Book, 1842 September 2-1843 April 6 (Volume 90)
- Letter-copy Book, 1843 April 7-1844 March 8 (Volume 91)
- Letter-copy Book, 1844 January 1-September 5 (Volume 92)
- Letter-copy Book, 1844 September 6-1845 April 3 (Volume 93)
- Letter-copy Book, 1845 April 3-November 26 (Volume 94)
- Letter-copy Book, 1846 October 22-1847 February 26 (Volume 95)
- Letter-copy Book, 1847 February 27-June 11 (Volume 96)
- Letter-copy Book, 1848 March 2-July 24 (Volume 97)
- Letter-copy Book, 1849 April 16-August 21 (Volume 98)
- Letter-copy Book, 1849 August 21-1850 January 7 (Volume 99)
- Letter-copy Book, 1850 January 7-May 17 (Volume 100)
- Letter-copy Book, 1850 May 17-September 23 (Volume 101)
- Letter-copy Book, 1850 September 24-1851 January 16 (Volume 102)
- Letter-copy Book, 1851 January 16-April 22 (Volume 103)
- Letter-copy Book, 1851 September 17-1852 February 11 (Volume 104)
- Letter-copy Book, 1853 March 3-June 20 (Volume 105)
- Letter-copy Book, 1853 June 20-October 14 (Volume 106)
- Letter-copy Book, 1853 October 15-1854 February 20 (Volume 107)
- Letter-copy Book, 1854 February 20-June 12 (Volume 108)
- Letter-copy Book, 1854 June 12-September 25 (Volume 109)
- Letter-copy Book, 1855 October 8-1856 February 15 (Volume 110)
- Letter-copy Book, 1873 September 30-1877 October 17 (Volume 111)
- Letter-copy Book, 1881 April 26-1883 February 20 (Volume 112)
- Letter-copy Book, 1886 March 8-1889 January 22 (Volume 113)
- Letter-copy Book, 1889 January 22-1890 November 24 (Volume 114)
- Letter-copy Book, 1892 May 5-1893 February 14 (Volume 115)
- Letter-copy Book, 1893 March 15-1894 January 9 (Volume 116)
- Letter-copy Book, 1894 January 17-November 8 (Volume 117)
- Letter-copy Book, 1894 November 8-1895 August 17 (Volume 118)
- Letter-copy Book, 1896 April 22-December 5 (Volume 119)
- Letter-copy Book, 1896 December 5-1897 April 26 (Volume 120)
- Letter-copy Book, 1897 April 24-September 28 (Volume 121)
- Letter-copy Book, 1897 September 28-1898 February 10 (Volume 122)
- Letter-copy Book, 1900 January 26-April 5 (Volume 123)
- Letter-copy Book, 1900 June 6-August (Volume 124)
- Letter-copy Book, 1900 August 8-October 2 (Volume 125)
- Letter-copy Book, 1903 February 20-June 20 (Volume 126)
- Letter-copy Book, 1912 July 5-1913 February 15 (Volume 127)
- Letters, 1863-1865 (Volume 128)
- Letters, 1877-1883 (Volume 129)
- Letters, 1883-1887 (Volume 130)
- Meat Market Account Book, 1916-1919 (Volume 131)
- Memorandum Book, 1975 (Volume 132)
- Memorandum Book, Undated (Volume 133)
- Mortgage Accounts, 1840-1842 (Volume 134)
- Mortgage Accounts, 1842-1843 (Volume 135)
- Mortgage Accounts, 1849-1850 (Volume 136)
- Mortgage Accounts, 1851-1852 (Volume 137)
- Mortgage Accounts, 1852-1853 (Volume 138)
- Mortgage Accounts, 1856-1857 (Volume 139)
- Mortgage Accounts, 1857-1863 (Volume 140)
- Mortgage Accounts, 1861-1868 (Volume 141)
- Notebook about a coin collection, Undated (Volume 142)
- Passenger List, 1832-1857 (Volume 143)
- Petty Cash Book, 1854-1858 (Volume 144)
- Photograph Album, Undated; 12 Digital Files (Volume 145)
- Photograph Album, Undated; 12 Digital Files (Volume 146)
- Photograph Album, Undated; 15 Digital Files (Volume 147)
- Receipts, 1842-1847 (Volume 148)
- Register, 1882-1888 (Volume 149)
- Ship Receipts, 1856-1857 (Volume 150)
- Ship Receipts, 1857-1859 (Volume 151)
- Ship Receipts, 1859-1861 (Volume 152)
- Sterling Bills, 1849-1858 (Volume 153)
- Storage and Delivery, 1844-1845 (Volume 154)
- Sundry Collections, 1856-1858 (Volume 155)
- Trust Accounts, 1870-1897 (Volume 156)
- Untitled account book, with running heading: Names, Belfast, London, Currency, 1857-1858 (Volume 157)
- Diary of a trip to Wales, 1812 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 1)
- Diary of a trip on the Ausable River and to Little Tupper Lake, Undated (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 2)
- List of books in a personal library, Undated (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 3)
- Johnson, Jane. Essays on Some of the Testimonies of Truth, as held by the Society of Friends. Philadelphia: Book Association of Friends, 1868 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 4)
- The Holy Bible, Containing the Old and New Testaments: Translated Out of the Original Tongues, and with the Former Translations Diligently Compared and Revised,by His Majesty's Special Comman. Edinburgh: Sir D. Hunter Blair and J. Bruce, 1821 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 5)
- English Reader, Undated (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 6)
- Moore, Chas. B. Collision Case; Opinion of Arbitrator, 1860 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 7)
- Scrapbook of Lizzie Thomas and Harvey Bell, 1850s (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 8)
- Scrapbook of Miss Harriet Thomas, Undated (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 9)
- The Philadelphia Album and Ladies' Literary Port Folio, 1831 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 10)
- Supreme Court. Abraham Bell, vs. Daniel H. Tompkins, et al. New York: Banks, Gould & Co., 1855 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 11)
- Heath, Mr. Charles, The New Gallery of British Engravings; a Selection of the Best Plates Published in the Works, London, David Bogue, 1846 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 12)
- Folder containing pictures, photographs, and an original drawing, Undated (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 13)
- Wright, Thomas, The History of Ireland from the Earliest Period of the Irish Annals, to the Present Time, London and New York: John Tallis and Co., Pts. 2-5, 1854 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 14)
- Carey, Rosa N., Queenie's Whim, New York: George Munro, 1883 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 15)
- James, G. P. R., The King's Highway, Undated (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 16)
- The Neptune Vase, Undated (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 17)
- Alexander, Mrs., The Admiral's Ward, New York: George Munro, 1883 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 18)
- United States Coast Pilot: Atlantic Coast. Part VI. Chesapeake Bay and Tributaries. Washington: Gov't Printing Office, 1889 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 19)
- Worcester, J. E., An Historical Atlas, Boston: Hilliard, Gray, Little, and Wilkins, 1828 (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 20)
- A Memorial of Mary Christy Harvey, Daughter of Reuben and Hannah C. Harvey, [1858] (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 21)
- Stabler, James P. The Certain Evidences of Practical Religion, Described in Letters to a Distant Relative, Undated (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 22)
- What is the Society of Friends? (Quakers), Pamphlet, Undated (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 23)
- Photocopy of pages from a scrapbook with items referring to the Bell Family, Undated (Box 1 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 24)
- Accounts current, 1838-1842 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 1)
- Accounts for building repairs, 1898-1899 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 2)
- Advertisements, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 3)
- Bills of lading, 1851 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 4)
- Bonds and mortgages, 1896-1900 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 5)
- Bond lists, 1899 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 6)
- Checks, 1835-1853 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 7)
- Checks, 1854-1917 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 8)
- Conowingo Bridge materials (miscellaneous), Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 9)
- Conowingo Bridge return tolls/tickets collected, 1890 - 1899 June 30 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 10)
- Conowingo Bridge return tolls/tickets collected, 1899 July 1-December 31 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 11)
- Conowingo Bridge - Shares of L. M. Kent, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 12)
- Contracts, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1837-1879 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1880-1899 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1900-1961 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 16)
- Correspondence, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 17)
- Deeds, 1839; 1864 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 18)
- Estate of James C. Bell in account with Bell Bros., weekly account statements, 1896-1899 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 19)
- Financial statements, 1896-1899 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 20)
- Fire insurance statement, 1896 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 21)
- Interest collections, 1916 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 22)
- Land sales, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 23)
- Lease for property in Maryland, 1866-1867 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 24)
- Letterheads and engravings, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 25)
- List of tax certificates, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 26)
- Loan applications, 1895-1899 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 27)
- Map releases, 1896 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 28)
- McDowell, E. B. - Contracts and correspondence, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 29)
- Newspaper articles (miscellaneous), Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 30)
- Office supplies, 1899 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 31)
- Papers (miscellaneous), Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 32)
- Patents, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 33)
- Real estate materials, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 34)
- Real property tax receipts, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 35)
- Receipts, general, 1835-1887 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 36)
- Receipts, general, 1888-1917 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 37)
- Receipts for safe deposit vault, 1905-1912 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 38)
- Taxes and assessment sales, 1896-1899 (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 39)
- Will and testament - Philip E. Thomas, Undated (Box 2 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection), Folder 40)
- Personal diaries of J. Wethered Bell, 1862-1917 (Box 3 (Abraham Bell and Son Collection))